Richard Nelson collection of Connecticut Stonewall Foundation Records GLBTQ.2012.04
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Richard Nelson Collection of Connecticut Stonewall Foundation Records
1985-2008
GLBTQ.2012.04
Connecticut Polish American Archives
1.0 Linear feet
Richard Nelson, long time member of the activist coalition Connecticut Stonewall Foundation, was an activist for gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender rights. The collection includes materials pertaining to events put on by the Connecticut Stonewall Foundation and specific writing and speeches done by Richard Nelson.
Biographical/Historical note
The Connecticut Stonewall Foundation was founded in 1985. The group held educational seminars, lectures, events, and conferences to educate gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender people and the general public regarding GLBTQ contributions to the world’s culture, common history, and present day issues. Working with other organizations like The Gay, Lesbian, and Straight Teachers Network, Connecticut Women’s Education and Legal Fund, Children From the Shadows, CT NOW, The Women’s Center at Trinity College, The Gay & Lesbian Film Festival, and various religious organizations, among others, the Foundation dealt with issues concerning the GLBTQ community culturally, politically, and socially. Richard Nelson was the Education Program Director of the Connecticut Stonewall Foundation and an avid activist for the gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender community in Connecticut.
Scope and Contents note
The collection spans a time period from 1985 to 2008 and includes correspondence, newspaper articles, exhibit planning materials, memorabilia, brochures, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open for research.
Nelson, Richard; Connecticut Stonewall Foundation; Gay artists -- History; Gay liberation movement -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Gay liberation movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Gays -- Connecticut -- Exhibitions; Lesbians -- Connecticut -- Exhibitions
- Stonewall Foundation- By-laws, mailing list, history of events, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Stonewall Foundation- Meeting agendas, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Richard Nelson- Writing pieces, speech, photos, 2002-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Exhibit- Timeline of GLBTQ history, 1900-1999. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Exhibit- “Challenging and Changing America: An Exhibition on the Struggle for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Civil Rights”- Description, advertising, articles, correspondence, photos- Hartford Public Library, Central Connecticut State University, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Exhibit- Materials #1- Photos, memorabilia, stickers of GLBTQ events. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Exhibit- Materials #2- Photos, articles. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Exhibit- Selection of writings used on large entrance walls of exhibit- Reprints of articles, leaflets, written works from over a long period of history. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Exhibit- Building the exhibit- Room notes, arrangement notes, 1999. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Exhibit- Wall label drafts (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Exhibit- Photos of exhibit opening (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Exhibit- University of Connecticut and Central Connecticut State University archives used- Loan agreement (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Hate Crimes- Correspondence, articles, legislation., 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hate Crimes- “What is Hate Speech” Panel- brochures, flyers, discussion materials, 2000. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Hate Crimes- Eminem’s lyrics- Press Conference to protest Hartford Civic Center concert, 2000; newspaper articles. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Equality Begins at Home- Calendar of events, newsletter, 1999. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Ballet Russes Exhibit- Committee for Truth in Art- Wadsworth Athenaeum, 1997-2000- Newspaper articles, debates. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Dr. Simon Karlinsky- “Committee for Truth in Art: Breaking the Silence of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Invisibility” lecture- itinerary, program, published works, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Ballet Russes Exhibit- “When do Biography and Art Intersect?”- correspondence, articles, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Robert K. Martin- “Reclaiming Our Lives”- GLBTQ and the arts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Connecticut Stonewall Foundation - events, correspondence, flyers, advertising, 1986-2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Church & State “Power Trip: A Special Report on Pat Robertson’s ‘Road to Victory’ Conference”- Vol. 48, No. 9 October, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Trinity College- “Celebrating Our Stories, Embracing Our Future” event- Flyers, photos, 1997. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Trinity College- “Celebrating Our Stories and Our Relationships” event- Programs, Richard Nelson speech, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Reverend Irene Monroe- Trinity College event- “The Role Religion Plays in Fostering Homophobia and Discrimination”; opinion pieces in Newsweekly, 1999. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- The Public Eye newsletter, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Surina Kahn The Public Eye “Gay Conservatives: Pulling the Movement to the Right”- Article, 1996; Presentation at UCONN Law School, 1999. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Transsexual Information- Articles, brochures, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- GLBTQ Brochures/Information (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Domestic partnership/ Same Sex marriage- Correspondence, articles, lobbying information., 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Challenging America Exhibit, 1999 - Binder with flyers, articles, and description of the exhibit. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Mounted photo of woman. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Voices in the wilderness: gay history: struggle and triumph for gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender civil rights - 1900-1999 [VHS and DVD] (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Poster made by Richard Nelson for Marriage Equality Rally, Hartford, May 16, 2004 (Oversize 1)